Michigan Conference of Congregational Christian Churches records, 1908-1964.
Congregational Library & Archives
Michigan Conference of Congregational Christian Churches records, 1908-1964.
RG4966
Congregational Library & Archives
1.09 Cubic Feet
(1 box)
The General Association of the Congregational Ministers and Churches of Michigan was formed on October 12, 1842. In 1908, it became known as the Michigan Conference. In 1932, the conference became known as the Michigan Conference of Congregational Christian Churches and in 1964 it became known as the Michigan Conference UCC. This collection includes trustee minutes and annual meeting minutes for the Congregational Association of Detroit as well as the records of women's missionary societies in the Congregational Association of Detroit and the Michigan Conference of Congregational Christian Churches.
Michigan Conference of Congregational Christian Churches
Congregational Association of Detroit
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Michigan Conference UCC, August 2011; accession 2011-4.
Additional materials donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Evangelical and Reformed Historical Society, March 2021; accession 2021-04.
Historical Note
The General Association of the Congregational Ministers and Churches of Michigan was formed on October 12, 1842. In 1908, the name of the statewide association was changed to "conference" while the regional conferences formally became "associations." As a result, the statewide association became the Michigan Congregational Conference. Likewise, the conference that covered the Detroit metropolitan, which had been in existence since 1887, became the Congregational Association of Detroit. In 1932, following the formation of the General Council of the Congregational Christian Churches at the national level in 1931, the Michigan Conference was renamed to the Michigan Conference of Congregational Christian Churches (also sometimes called Michigan Congregational and Christian Conference). In 1964, following the formation of the United Church of Christ at the national level in 1957, the Michigan Conference reformed as the Michigan Conference UCC. As a part of that process, the Detroit Association formally joined with the Michigan Conference UCC and became known as the Detroit Metropolitan Association. Both Conference and Association continue to exist today.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records related to the Congregational Association of Detroit and the Michigan Congregational Christian Conference. The bulk of the records are related to the Congregational Association of Detroit and include annual meeting minutes, trustee meeting minutes, and the records of the Women's Union, Women's Missionary Union, and Women's Fellowship. A smaller portion of records are from the Michigan Congregational Christian Conference (sometimes also called the Michigan Congregational and Christian Conference, the Michigan Congregational Conference, or the Michigan Congregational Association) and this portion includes records from Women's missionary organizations, clippings related to the merger, and a folder of financial records for the Century Fund.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection have been arranged into the two series listed below. Within each series, materials have been arranged in chronological order by start date.
Series 1: Congregational Association of Detroit records, 1908-1964
Series 1: Michigan Congregational Christian Conference records, 1936-1963
Related Materials
Wenstrom, Donald A. A history of the Michigan Conference United Church of Christ and its parent denominations, 1842-1992. Michigan Conference, UCC: 2001. Call number 9.3.282
Detroit Congregational Union records, 1908-1937. RG 4973
Detroit Metropolitan Association mortgage, 1968. RG5421
Clergy conferences.; Home missions.; Women in church work.; Michigan Conference of Congregational Christian Churches; Congregational Association of Detroit
- Congregational Association of Detroit records, 1908 1964; 1908-1964; 1 Volume; 24 Folders
  - Women's Missionary Union minutes, 1908 1925; 1908-1925 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Women's Missionary Union records, 1926 1938; 1926-1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Financial ledger, 1926 1942; 1926-1942 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Women's Union records, 1927 1938; 1927-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Women's Union executive committee records, 1928 1933; 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Women's Missionary Union registration book, 1929 1944; 1929-1944 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Women's Union records, 1933 1937; 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Trustee meetings and annual meetings, 1935 1937; 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Trustee minutes, 1937 1940; 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women's Union records, 1937 1941; 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annual meetings, 1938 1946; 1938-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Trustee minutes, 1941 1946; 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women's Union records, 1941 1947; 1941-1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Education committee records, 1941 1948; 1941-1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual meetings, 1946 1957; 1946-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trustee minutes, 1947 1949; 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Women's Fellowship minutes, 1947 1950; 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Trustee minutes, 1950 1952; 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Education committee records, 1950 1952; 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Women's Fellowship constitution and meeting minutes, 1950 1955; 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Women's Fellowship minutes, 1951 1952; 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Trustee minutes, 1953 1956; 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Trustee minutes, 1957 1962; 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Trustee minutes, 1962 1964; 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Official actions, 1961 1962; 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Michigan Congregational Christian Conference records, 1936 1963; 1936-1963; 5 Folders
  - Women's Department records, 1936 1938; 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Century fund records, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Women's Work annual reports, 1938 1939; 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Women's Fellowship manual and meeting minutes, 1955 1963; 1955-1963 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Merger clippings, 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)